Preliminary Guide to the Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library records, 1925-1989 RG0058
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library records
1925-1989
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library
RG0058
11 Linear Feet
Materials in this collection include accession books, office files, correspondence, and film, video, and oral histories. They range in date from 1931 to 1980.
no content
Restrictions on Access
Series 2 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials were transferred to the University Archives by the Director of the Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library is part of The George Washington University Medical Center. It opened in 1973, when the new medical school (located in Ross Hall) moved from 1337 H Street, N.W. to its current location in Foggy Bottom. The Paul Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library and the Walter G. Ross Hall were dedicated May 24, 1973. The dedication address was delivered by Caspar W. Weinberger, then Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare.
The Library was a vast improvement on the previous, which had been very cramped and poorly staffed. The bulk of funding for the new building came from Paul Himmlefarb, a self-taught Jewish immigrant who came to Baltimore from Poland in 1890. He made his fortune in oil and real estate and later became a philanthropist. His gift made possible the library named after him, a $10 million structure which was designed to seat 399 readers within its three stories of public space. Its capacity was expandable to 80,000 volumes and 1,500 periodicals, and its audio visual center was among the first of its kind in the nation.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include accession books, office files, correspondence, and film, video, and oral histories. They range in date from 1931 to 1980, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Director of the Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Office files; Accession books; Film and video.
Videotapes; Washington (D.C.); Moving images; Young, Isabella; George Washington University
- Office files, 1932-1989; RG0058 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes brochures, correspondence, bibliographies, reports, and lists. They range in date from 1932 to 1989. The items are about audiovisual materials, periodicals, serials, books, student workers, annual reports, Isabella Young's correspondence, and general information about the library.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Library, Medical, 09/1973-12/1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Library, Medical - Annual and Periodic Reports to the University Librarian, 06/15/1932-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Library--Medical--Book lists, 1966-1974, 1966-03/1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Library--Medical Librarian--Isabella Young--Correspondence, 11/01/1943-02/03/1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Accession books, 1931-1980; RG0058 Series 2; 2.0 Linear feet
  This series contains accession listings of books. These records cover the dates 1931-80.
  Formerly ACC #74, Formerly RG 7.2.1
  - Accession records, 1931-1980; Series 2 Box 1; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    This box contains two books and multiple folders of accession records for the library.
- Film and tape, RG0058 Series 3; .25 Linear feet (Box 2)
  This series contains four audio cassettes with oral histories, two videotapes, and 2 films.
  - Videotape of convocation which honored Ronald and Nancy Reagan, 1991, 03/28/1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    General note
    This is the videotape is entitled, "Convocation: Honoring Ronald & Nancy Reagan". It dates to March 28, 1991 and is 64:11 minutes long.
  - Videotape of the 19th Annual Brian Blades Memorial Lecture, 1996, 10/17/1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    This is the videotape is the 19th Annual Brian Blades Memorial Lecture. It dates to October 17, 1996.
  - Film: "New Medical School", 10/17/1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    This item is 16mm black & white film entitled, "New Medical School". This film dates ca. 1973.
  - Film: "New Medical School", 10/17/1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)